"Is Obesity Caused by a GLP-1
Hormone Deficiency?"
Can we drug our way
out of the obesity crisis?
This 60 Minutes episode
certainly seemed to suggest
we could.
Only later did we learn
that 60 Minutes had been paid
by the makers of Ozempic
to air a 13-minute
promotional segment
and pass it off
as a news story.
Are these GLP-1 drugs the answer
to the obesity epidemic?
The head of
the European Association
for the Study of Obesity
was pretty bullish,
conveniently failing to disclose
that his group had received
millions of dollars
from the drug maker.
But doesn’t getting
a tiny weekly injection
sound far easier than getting
all sweaty in the gym?
Do these game-changing
new medications
"make lifestyle-based treatment
of obesity obsolete"?
Let’s ask those paid by
the two main GLP-1 drug makers,
which now have
a combined net worth
greater than a trillion dollars.
The World Obesity Federation,
which evidently just got
a million dollars
from the Ozempic company,
published a consensus statement
in one of its journals
favoring the definition
of obesity as a disease.
This designation
may not benefit patients,
but it will benefit doctors
and drug companies
when health insurance
and clinical guidelines
promote treatment
with drugs and surgery.
A concern is that labeling
obesity as a disease
risks reducing our autonomy,
disempowering and robbing us
of the intrinsic motivation
that’s an important enabler
of change.
It encourages fatalism,
promoting the fallacy
that genetics are destiny.
But, of course,
it can’t be our genes.
The obesity epidemic only
started a few decades ago.
Our genes didn’t somehow
magically change
in the late 1970s.
Others blame lack of willpower,
but that doesn’t make
any sense either.
All of us coincidentally lost
our collective self-control?
It’s the food.
The rise in the number
of excess calories
provided by the U.S. food supply
is more than sufficient
to explain the obesity epidemic.
Obesity is not
some moral failing.
The battle of the bulge is
a battle against biology.
We’re living
in a toxic food environment,
drowning in a sea
of excess calories,
being bombarded with ads
for fast food and candy.
Becoming overweight is
a normal, natural response
to the abnormal,
unnatural ubiquity
of sugary, fatty foods that are
concentrated with calories.
So, the prime cause
for the obesity epidemic
is neither gluttony nor sloth.
Being overweight may simply be
a normal response,
by normal people,
to an abnormal situation.
And with nearly three-quarters
of Americans overweight,
it’s literally normal.
So, if obesity is
to be understood
as "normal physiology within
a pathological environment,"
there is an argument
that drugs like Ozempic
really aren’t tackling
the root cause of obesity.
These drugs will likely have
only a modest effect
on reducing
the rapidly growing epidemic
and may even make it worse,
as Big Pharma and its lobbyists
try to shift society’s focus
to drugs
rather than broader
public health strategies.
The real solution would involve
fixing the food system,
but why would Big Food
change its ways
if obesity can be treated
with drugs?
So, the main actors responsible
for creating and perpetuating
the obesity-generating world
will continue undisturbed.
England’s health secretary
was keen to use GLP-1 drugs
as a "way of preventing illness
without resorting
to ’nanny state’ measures,"
but advocates are just
talking about things like
restricting the thousands of ads
kids see every year
for candy, liquid candy
(soft drinks),
breakfast candy, and fast food.
A quarter century ago,
the term "Social Determinants
of Health" was coined,
defined as the nonmedical
factors that influence health
too often ignored
by the medical establishment,
such as poverty.
They explain why the top
1 percent, for example,
live about 10 to 15 years longer
than the bottom 1 percent.
More recently,
based on experience
with the alcohol
and tobacco industries,
the concept of "Commercial
Determinants of Health"
was introduced,
which can be defined as
"factors that influence health
which stem from the profit
motive," also referred to
as the Corporate
Determinants of Health.
The food and beverage sectors
spend huge amounts
on developing
and marketing products
packed with sugar,
fat, and salt,
deliberately designed
to lead to addictive consumption
that contributes
to the increasing prevalence
of chronic disease.
Public corporations like
Coca-Cola have a legal duty
to maximize return
to their shareholders,
and those running the companies
are heavily incentivized
to achieve this.
Many observers are outraged
by stories
of what some of these companies
do to maximize returns,
but as people working in the
tobacco industry can testify,
being the subject
of widespread disrepute
is more than offset
by the financial rewards.
And psychological defense
mechanisms can take care
of any residual unease about
contributing to the suffering
and death of fellow humans whom
they do not personally know.
The greatest challenge
to improving health may lie
in the tension between
wealth creation
and health creation.